Finding Aid for Rentschler's Studio photograph collection, 1889-1969
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Rentschler's Studio photograph collection 1889-1969
Rentschler's Studio (Ann Arbor, Mich.)
9097 UBB.2 2
Ann Arbor, Michigan photographic studio. Collection includes selected copy prints, and glass and film negatives relating to University of Michigan athletics, both photos of individual athletes and of team groupings; also photos of various faculty and University administrators and log books of photos.
3 volumes
275 prints
600 negatives in 8 boxes
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was given to the library in 1983 by Lois Rentschler (Donor No. 6950) and Herbert Pfabe, Sr (Donor No. 5377)
No further additions to the collection expected.
The collection is open without restriction except for the 11 x 14 glass negatives of the football team photos which have been scanned and are available through the Bentley Library Image Bank.
Born in Ann Arbor in 1868, J. Fred Rentschler became the city's most respected portrait photographer. After serving as an apprentice at the Gibson studios, Rentschler opened his own studio in 1890. He operated Rentschler's Studios until his death in 1940. At that time, his son Edwin D. Rentschler took over the business. When Edwin died in 1971, the studio soon ceased operation under the Rentschler name.
The Rentschler Studios collection is made up of nearly 625 negatives and 275 copy prints. It comprises five linear feet and is stored in seven boxes, four large and three small. The collection also includes the studio's log books of photos. The photographs span the years from 1889 to 1969. Although the Rentschlers operated a private studio, over two-thirds of the portraits are of persons directly affiliated with the University of Michigan. The two largest categories of portraits are: 1) faculty and administrators and 2) athletes, teams, and coaches. There are also portraits of students, clergy, businessmen, city officials, and others.
The collection is divided into three series, Negatives, Prints, and Log Books. Glass and film negatives comprise the vast majority of the collection and are arranged into four subseries: Numerical; Team Portraits; Miscellaneous; and Football Team Portraits, 1896-1942. The smaller series - Prints - is located in Box 4 and is arranged into two subseries: Athletics and Portraits.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Dewey, Thomas E. (Thomas Edmund), 1902-1971.; Photographs.; Rentschler's Studio (Ann Arbor, Mich.); University of Michigan--Sports.; University of Michigan--Baseball.; University of Michigan--Basketball.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan--Football.; University of Michigan--Golf.; University of Michigan--Tennis.; University of Michigan--Track and field.; University of Michigan--Wrestling.
Contributors:
Rentschler, Edwin D., 1900-1971.; Rentschler, J. Fred, 1869-1940.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Negatives
  The Negatives series, glass and film negatives, comprises the vast majority of the collection and are arranged into four subseries: Numerical; Team Portraits; Miscellaneous; and Football Team Portraits, 1896-1942.
  The Numerical subseries of the Negatives series is stored in the first three boxes. The portraits in this subseries have been indexed by the subject's name. There are three indexes: athletes and coaches, faculty and administrators, and a third index for those individuals who do not fit into the first two categories.
  Team Portraits include lengthy runs of the football, baseball, basketball, golf, gymnastics, track, and wrestling teams for the years 1948-1969. Only football team portraits are extensive before World War II. However, as these early football team portraits from 1896-1942 are outsize glass negatives, they are stored separately in the Football Team Portraits, 1896-1942 subseries in Boxes 5 to 7.
  The Miscellaneous Negatives subseries consists of two negative boxes, containing approximately eighty negatives of miscellaneous unindexed portraits. All portraits in this subseries are from the 1950s and 1960s.
  - Numerical
    (mostly 5x7 glass negatives, with a few 8x10 glass negatives)
    [see index below for item listing)
    - 05010-29999 (Box 1)
    - 30000-57999 (Box 2)
    - 58000-84999 (Box 3)
    - U001-U010
  - Team Photos
    - Football
      (see also outsize glass negatives in boxes 5-7 for team photos, 1898-1942)
      - Copy negatives 1884, 1887-1890, 1894-1898, 1902, 1918 (Box 4)
      - Original negatives 1943-1968 (Box 4)
    - Baseball
      - Copy Negatives 1875, 1892, 1896, 1899, 5x7 glass negatives (Box 4)
      - Original negatives 1947-1967 (Box 4)
    - Basketball
      - 1947-1969 (Box 4)
      - 1965-1966, color negatives (Box 4)
    - Golf 1947-1969, 1948 junior team (Box 4)
    - Gymnastics 1949-1957 (Box 4)
    - Swimming 1948-1951 (Box 4)
    - Tennis 1963-1968 (Box 4)
    - Track (Box 4)
      - 1896, 1898, 1900, circa 1900, 5x7 glass negatives
      - 1948-1969, 1968 relay team, 8x10 and 5x7 film negatives
    - Wrestling 1947, 1951-1953, 1955-1965 (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous Negatives
    - Portraits 1950s and 1960s, 100 negatives b/w; number approximate 5x7 (Box 4)
      (identified only by last name)
    - Portraits and Copy Negatives, 100 negatives approximate number; black and white 5x7 (Box 4)
      (original negatives and some copy negatives, some identified by last name)
- Prints
  In the Prints series, the Athletics subseries generally duplicates the team portrait negatives. There are, however, five folders of senior portraits of football players for 1965-1969. A complete list of senior portraits follows the index of athletes and coaches.
  The Portraits subseries of prints is comprised of two folders of portraits, many unidentified. Those which have been identified are indexed with the negatives.
  - Athletics
    (8x10 team photos from Rentschler negatives unless otherwise stated)
    - Baseball 1950-1967 (Box 4)
    - Basketball 1949-1969 (Box 4)
    - Football
      - Team photos 1943-1968 (Box 4)
      - Senior portraits 1965-1969, 5 folders (Box 4)
        (see attached listing of names)
    - Golf 1961-1969 (Box 4)
    - Tennis 1967 (Box 4)
    - Track 1950-1969 (Box 4)
    - Wrestling 1965-1967 (Box 4)
  - Portraits
    - Identified (Box 4)
    - Unidentified (Box 4)
- Negatives
  - Team Photos
    - Football Team Photos 1896-1942, 11" x 14" glass negatives"
      - 1896, 1898-1910 (Box 5)
      - 1911-1926 (Box 6)
      - 1927-1942 (Box 7)
- Log Books
  The Log Books series, consists of two volumes of logs of the subjects of the studio's photo work and one address book. The first log book volume labeled "Faculty and Prominent People." Both log books are arranged alphabetically and include the name of the person and the negative number. The surviving negatives in the collection are only a small subset of the items recorded into log books. The address book includes and index and photos of All-Americans and football captains in addition to business and personal addresses. The indexes in this finding aid can be used in lieu of the indexes in these volumes.
  - Photo log books, 2 volumes (Box 8)
  - Address Book (Box 8)
To help locate photographs quickly, the three following indexes have been prepared. They are: 1) Athletes and Coaches Index, 2) Faculty and Administrators Index and 3) Miscellaneous Index. The first two indices include only the names of persons who clearly fall into these categories. Therefore, if one is looking for a particular athlete or professor, it would be advisable to also consult the Miscellaneous Index. A negative number beside the name indicates the availability of a negative. The location is determined by the number. Numbers 05010-29999 are in Box 1, numbers 30000-57999 in Box 2, numbers 58000-84999 and U001-U010 in Box 3. If the word “print” follows the entry, the image is available on a print. These are located in Box 4 in the folder labeled “Portraits, identified, A-Z.”
Athletes and Coaches Index
Allerdice, David Way 19712, 83470 (copy)
Austin, Thomas D. 57453
Baird, Charles 07020, 07893(2)
Baird, Charles and Fitzpatrick, Keene 13397
Bernard, Charles 60947
Benbrook, Albert W. 57610
Blott, Jack 42423, 42425
Blott, Jack L. 72952
Brown 43420
Cachey, Ted 79856
Caithamel, George (Ceithamel) 66055
Chappuis, Bob 74422
Cochrane, William 26923, 83470 (copy)
Conklin, Fred 22183, 83470 (copy)
Craig, James 25477, na 9392 print
Cress, Earl 80524
Crisler, Herbert O. "Fritz" (coach) 75895, 82009, 84652(2)
Culver, Frank U-004
Cunningham, William 64820 (copy)
Curtis, John Spencer 12383, 83470 (copy)
Daley, Bill 73287
Dunne, Jerome 37376, 83470 (copy)
Elliott, Coach (Bump) 82289(2)
Evashevski, Forest. 63156
Fay, Stan 54448
Fitzpatrick, Keene 9847
Fitzpatrick, Keene with Baird, Charles 13397
Franks, Julius F. 67571
Friedman, Benny 45238, 83470 (copy)
Goebel, Paul 57610
Goetz, Angus G. 35240, 83470 (copy)
Graver, Herbert 09587a
Green, Merritt 78172
Gregory, George W. 09570(2), 10935(2)
Gregory, George W. with Heston, W.M. 09587, 12235
Hahn, Archie (track) 10690(2)
Hammond, Tom 12193
Harmon, Tom 63026(2)
Heikkinen, Ralph 61877
Herrnstein, Abert E. 07001, 09328
Heston, Willie 09571(2), 09587, 12234(2)
Heston, Willie w/Gregory, George 09587, 12235
Heston, Willie w/Yost, Fielding H. 13703
Heyliger, Vic (hockey coach) 81220
Hilkene, Bruce 74042
Hollway, Robert 74000
Hubbard, William DeHart. (track) 42178, na 9664
Hudson, Roy. 52478, 83470 (copy)
Janke, Fred C. 61255
Jones, Paul 12203
Kipke, Harry C. 40887, 60123 - na 13,744
Kodros, Archie J. 62364
Kramer, Ron 80259
Lawton, George 19725
Little, George (football coach) 40571
McCoy, Ernie B. ?
McGoffin, Paul P. 13672, 83470 (copy)
McGugin, Dan 09564 (2)
Maddock, Joseph 10950
Mann, Matthew (swimming coach) 61007
Maulbetsch, John F. 29493, 83470 (copy)
Meads, Ed 80350
Meentz, Tom 80820
Miller, Wayne (?) (wrestling) 83970
Morrison, Maynard D. 53623
Newman, Harry 57609
Norcross, Fred S. 12194, 12433
Oosterbaan, Bennie G. 46638, 76561
Orwig, Bill (coach) 79653
Orwig, Jim 81488
O'Shaughnessy, Richard 79059
Pace, James 80451
Patanelli, Mathew 58739, 83470 (copy)
Paterson, George 25034, 83470 (copy)
Perry, Lowell U-002
Petoskey, Fred U-003
Pommerening, Otto P. 49318
Ponsetto, Joe. (in naval uniform) 72878
Pregulman, Mervin 70412
Putich, Bill 77336
Raynsford, Janes W. 27408, 83470 (copy)
Redden, Curtis 07003, 10912
Renner, Art 73283
Renner, Bill 57517
Rifenberg, Dick 75513(2)
Rinaldi, Joe 60174
Rich, George 47496
Rose, Ralph Warwick (track) 12955(2)
Schulte, Henry 13642
Schulz, Adolph "Germany" 13664(2)
Simrall, James 83470 (copy)
Slaughter, Edliff 43583, na 9391 print
Smith, Cedric C. 30802, 83470 (copy)
Snow, Neil (baseball) 07655
Snow, Neil (football) 07004
Snow, Neil (track) 09169(2)
Steger, Herb 43406, 83470 (copy)
Steketee, Frank 57609 (copy)
Sweeley, Everett M. 07007
Thompson, George C. 22368, 83470 (copy)
Tomasi, Dominic 74819
Truskowski, Joseph E. 49697
Vick, Ernie (baseball) 57609 (2 copies)
Uteritz, Irwin C. (baseball) 39528
Wahl, Robert (Al) 76157
Walker, Art 80531
Webber, Wally .J. (coach) 64932
Weber, Wally (coach) 80429
Weeks, Harrison "Boss". 07010(2), 12209(2)
Wells, Stanfield 19726(2), na 9393 print
Westfall, Bob 64935(2)
White, Hugh. 07008
White, Paul 67612
Wieman, Elton E. 37063(2), 46558, 83470 (copy)
Wiese, Bob 71012
Williams, J.B. 54197
Wistert, Albert 67505
Wistert, Alvin 5511
Wistert, Francis U-005, na 9390, print
Yost, Fielding Harris 07538, 12442(2), 19775, 37203(2), 40925, 63713(2)
Yost, F.H. w/Heston, W.M. 13703
Yost, F.H. with others 11137-11138
Foot Captains (Hugh White, Neil Snow, Boss Weeks) 09626
Football, Beta members, 1967 84423
Ferry Field (1905, UM-Wisconsin game) 76542 (copy)
Pre-Rose Bowl training, 1947 84808 (copy)
Wolverines in California for first Rose Bowl game U-001 (copy)
Football Senior Portraits (2.75x3.75 b/w white prints, located in box 4)
1965
Bayster, Berline, Byers, Dayton, D'Eramo, Doty, Goss, Hanna, Heffelinger, Hollis, Johnson, Knapp, Landsittel, Mair, Morgan, Muir, Nowak, O'Donnell, Porter, Pullen, Rosema, Salmi, Sharpe, Sieber, Spencer, Thomas, Yednak
1966:
Adam, Baumgartner, Brown, Frysinger, Hartman, Hoey, Hribal, Humphries, Jobe, Johnson, Ron; Kietg, Kramer, Kunsa, Miklos, Nelson, Penksa, Phillips, Radigan, Reynolds, Salt, Sipp, Stincic, Tackett, Wedge, Wilhite, Williamson, Yanz
1967:
Barnes, Bolduc, Brown, r., Craw, Doane, Drehmann, Federico, Gabler, Goodman, Hall, Harris, Healy, Kenney, Lukz, Mandich, Marley, Monthei, Mouch, Pierson, Pniewski, Prusiecki, Sansom, Sarantos, Seymour, Sorenson, Wall, Weinmann, Werner, White, Wooley
1968
Abrahams, Baldwin, Berotti, Betts, Catallo, Denzin, Dierdorf, Dutcher, Falkenhagen, Farabee, Flanagan, Francis, Al; Harrison, Hill, Henry; Huff, Imsland, Kitzmiller, Kohn, McCaffrey, McCoy, Mandler, Moore, Newell, Perkins, Ritley, Sample, Sams, Schleffler, Sirosky, Staroba, Titas, Wilhite
1969:
Beckman, Betts, Branstatter, Carpenter, Curtis, Darden, Elliott, Grambau, Gusich, Hall, Huiskens, Jones, Keller, McKenzie, Mandich, Murdock, Seyferth, Shaw, Taylor, Bill; Taylor, Mike; Wadhams, Zucarelli, Zuganelis
Index to Faculty and Staff
Alt, Glenn L. 51001
Angell, James Burrill 05010(4)
Bailey, Benjamin Franklin 52905
Barker, Paul S. 53919
Bates, Henry M. 54146
Beal, Junius (in Knights Templar attire?) 08943
Belser, Martin Luther 07820
Bigelow, Melville Madison 09166
Bonisteel, M.F. 49881
Bonisteel, Roscoe prints (2)
Bursley, Philip Everette 51536
Burton, Marion LeRoy 37980
Coller, Frederick A. 53960
Cooley, Mortimer Elwyn 05070, 51570, 51576
Cooley, M.E. with dog 05070a, 05070b
Copeland, Royal S. 08286, 09654 (3)
Decker, Arthur J. w/Hoad, W. 81700
Dennison, Charles Simeon 16987
Dock, George 05080(2), 14447
Drake, Joseph Horace 12297, 51530
Eich, Louis Michael 52791
Glover, James Waterman 51400
Haight, Cameron 81345, print
Hall, Louis Phillips 06020
Hatcher, Harlan 78886, 78924, print
Herdman, William James 06000
Hewlett, Albion Walter 19566
Hoad, William C. w/Decker, A.J. 81700
Hobbs, William H. print
Hodges, Fred J. 53481?
Hoff, Nelville Soule 06015
Hussey, William Joseph 41021
Hutchins, Harry Burns 35976
Jellinek, Jerome print
Kauper, Paul G. ?
Knowlton, Jerome Cyril 06050
Lloyd, Alfred Henry 34285
Lombard, Warren Plimpton 07015
Lynds, James Gifford 06060
McCotter, Rollo Eugene 53948
McCoy, Lester prints(2)
Maxwell, James H. 53907
Myers, George Edmond 51551
O'Neill, J.M. 48164
O'Neill, J.N. 46392
Pattengill, Albert Henderson 06082
Randall, Willett F. 54069
Ransom, Henry K. 53868
Ruthven, Alexander G. 44455, 49530
Slocum, George 39287
Smith, Shirley 39543
Stanley, Albert Augustus 13251
Trueblood, Thomas C. 51447
Vaughan, Victor Clarence 11859, 37947
Warthin, Alfred Scott 06096(2), 34387
Wenley, Robert Mark 06094(2)
Whitman, Elmer L. 76720
Wilson, Frank N. 70547
Young, Leigh J. 71999
Index to Miscellaneous Individuals
Alexander, Dr. J. 50547
Ames, H.T. print
Andres 51218
Arrey print
Bach, Anna Botsford 13579
Bandemer, William E. print
Bottum, Eddie and dog 78021
Bowman, Rev. W.F. 36395
Bradley, Russel 81703
Brauer, Carl, Jr. print
Brown, Mayor W.E. 81340 na 9069
Burke, Dr. print
Burke, Louis E. print
Bury, Al 54860
Conklin print
Covey, M. 08933
Covly, C.H. 36658
Davis, Prof. B.J. 07455
Deborr, Richard (navy uniform) 78886
Delker, F.J.D. 81701
Del Toro, J. 51562
Dewey, Thomas (student photo) 38962 (2)
Dicken, C.D. 56413
Dumond, Caryl 78029
Eidson, Duane 77079
Fairbanks, A. 51031
Flemming, Rev. 05086
Fohey, Chief (fire department) 56174
Forshee, Jane ?
Forsythe, Dr. W.E. 48127, 51189
Frisinger, H.L. print
Frutig, Ed 62515
Godfrey 05090
Goldstein, David 78016
Green, Merritt 78172
Gross, Herman F. prints (3)
Gustine, Dick print
Gustine, N. print
Harriman, Judge 05095
Hemp, J.L., Sr. print
Henderson, Charles R. 76562(2)
Hill, C. print
Hill, Clara 77039
Hiscock, E.D. 08923
Kalorisdian, Al (copy neg. of old photos) 74610
Kelly, Rev. E.D. 21415
Kempf, R.H. 07492 (2)
Klingmann, Dr. T. 06048
Lucas, Ed (alderman) 52164
Lutzy, Dr. 06098
Mayerson prints (2)
Mickel, Frank 52639
Miller, R. 56118
Nancrede, Dr. 07016
Newman, Rev. 06078 (2)
Nouri, Jay 78017
Novey, F. 46526
Parker, Dr. W.R. 36483
Parnall, Dr. J.C. 76526
Peek, Monsignor G.W. 80868 (2)
Peterson, R.P. 46600
Ponsetto, J. 72878
Pray, J.G. 45483
Prevost, W.E. (baby) 78023
Proud, P. (Ann Arbor Club) 57138
Radas print
Randall, H.M. print
Reichart, R. 46457
Reichert, R. 66306
Reichert, V.G. 54021
Rentschler 82691
Rentschler, J. Fred 50000 (2)
Rentschler, Mrs. Ed 82000
Sawyer print
Schaible, Miss 46055
Schlanderer, P. 70901
Seeley, M.G. print
Seely, R. 09841
Sehdible, R.G. 77037
Slaek, E.J. 39046
Springer, W.D. 44069 (2)
Staebler, Ed 52753
Staebler, Neil print
Steeb, William G. 77331
von Rague, Rev. H.S. 73375
Waigler, Prof. R. 70935
Warner print
Wild, G.H. 07258
Wines 35505
Winkler, Dr. H.G. 70000
Withrow print
Zimmerman print
Zion Lutheran Church ministers 80497